dr stephen
now let us take the warmness
across to welcome dr stephen hover
hello taiban my name is stefan hofer and i love
a good story so imagine it is 20 000 years ago it
is in the middle of winter and the tribe of cave
people sit around a warm fire it is quiet except
for the cracking firewood then one of the elders
clears their throat many summers ago a large herd
of bison wandered through our hunting grounds it
was the largest herd that anyone had ever seen
and as the elder shares his story one of the
cave people starts to use colorful rocks and coal
to paint a picture and to this very day
we can see this picture in the cave wall
and in a sense that is what we want
to do with the main storytelling
we want to spark a fire tell
a story and paint a picture
storytelling is at the heart of human
communication and it still works in the
age of software the main storytelling is one
of the techniques that brings domain experts
product owners business analysts and
software development teams together
it helps them to overcome misunderstandings and
to establish a common language that helps you to
talk about business processes and requirements
or in short to build better business software
today i'm going to introduce you to domain
storytelling by showing you a short demo
then i will explain the method and
finally i will tell you a little
bit about the influence that ddd had on domain
storytelling and maybe also the influence that
ddd has that domain storytelling
has on ddd in its community
so i will tell you another story
this time it is about a software system that
my colleagues and i built a couple of years
ago it's a software system that was
supposed to help approve road work so what
happened was with a group of stakeholders and they
already had a set of requirements they said ah the
system must support issuing permits and the sector
system must support hearings and we need support
on reviewing applications and many more use cases
so the problem was that we didn't really
understand how all these isolated requirements
make up a whole software system for for
proving road work we hadn't really understood
the basic business processes behind it so
how does a proving roadwork typically work
that was the questions that we asked our domain
experts when we brought him together in a room
and in front of a whiteboard and
this is the story that holders
so construction company has won a tender for
a road work project and before they can start
they need to obtain a permit so that they
can close the road to traffic so the story
starts where the project supervisor awards
the contract to the construction company
and then they can submit the
application for the permit
using this new software system
that we were supposed to build
now the stakeholders told us that the
project supervisor should be notified
whenever a new application comes in because they
need to review the application and compare it
with the tender documents now we didn't
understand that requirement at first and
they explained us well there can be for example
different dates in the application than in the
tender documents if for example the construction
company doesn't have the necessary resources
or maybe the weather has changed then they need to
delay the construction work and that's why dates
could differ in the application for
the permit and in the tender documents
so once the application is reviewed another
role comes into play a traffic authority
they draft the permit
and they determine the concerned authorities
for a hearing so concerned authorities
those are for example police communities
public transport everyone who could
be affected by a construction site and
they get a link to the hearing documents
and can review the permit and they can submit
statements where they say either it's okay or
they can raise concerns like maybe they have
a marathon planned or something like that
that would have an influence
on the construction site
so the traffic authority then considers
these statements and issues the permit
and the permit is then sent
to the construction company
now this whole hearing process here and drafting
the permit and revising the draft considering the
statements made by the concerned authorities that
is something that can be repeated several times
but in this story we looked at a happy path
scenario so everything is fine the first draft
becomes the final permit and this is often
a typical way of using domain storytelling
we start with a happy path and then later look
into a more complicated variations of the process
so this little story and visualizing
that story helped us to understand in
much more detail what the
system was supposed to do
and this is one of the typical
cases for using domain storytelling
to think about new software systems and
how they should support business processes
now how does this method work
many people especially software developers tend
to think about business processes and visualize
business processes like this as a rather abstract
but complete description of everything that could
possibly happen so it's about different paths in
one picture with the main storytelling we choose a
different approach we think that a good example is
better than a bad abstraction so we want examples
first and from that knowledge from that foundation
we can later build abstractions in our software
so usual usually it's sufficient to model two
or three of the most important versions of the
business process so the happy path maybe an
important variation or common error scenario
so if we look at individual paths and
therefore we don't need any any
gateways or switches or ifs or
case statements in our pictographic language
now domain stories can have different
scopes the story that i showed you about
the construction site was i would say
about medium on a medium level of detail
to give you some more idea how domain stories can
can look i'll introduce you to another example
this time it's about a movie theater so on
the left side we see the process of going
to the movies so this is a end-to-end business
process from the customer's point of view so we
have a moviegoer here they buy a ticket from a
cashier and then you buy snacks and drinks from
a concession stand and they showed a ticket to the
usher to get access to the movie theater and so on
on the right side we see a much more
detailed picture that tells you the story
of buying tickets we have a moviegoer who
picks seats and buys for the tickets and so on
so time buying tickets was one step in the
course grade story on the left and it's now
a whole story on its own in the more detailed
story on the right and that's just one way of
illustrating different scopes of stories
now no matter the level of detail or the
scope of the story you will always need
a pictographic language to visualize it
so our pictographic language is comprised of a
set of symbols so we have actors the person or the
people or the software systems who
are active in the story who do things
and we have work objects those are the things that
they use it can be information physical things
digital objects with activities depicted
as arrows and we use textual annotations
now to give those icons a concrete meaning we
label them so we have a customer ticket bias and
so on and if we look at the pictographic
language in a little bit more detail
we can have for example different actors so most
commonly we use a single person a group of people
a system but depending on the domain that you're
in you can change and adapt the set of symbols
for example i did a couple of the main stories
in in the harbor domain so ships are important
actors there and then have a little
ship icon that represents a ship
the same is true for the work objects we also use
different icons there most commonly to express
the medium of a book object so for example if i
call the cashier in the box office of the cinema
and ask about a reservation for a movie tonight
and then i would draw this with a telephone icon
if they then send me a reservation as an email i
will use this email icon and if i decide to print
the reservation at home i will use the document
icon with that pictographic language we can build
sentences and the idea is that the sentence in the
pictographic language reads almost like you would
write a natural language sentence now to tell a
story we of course need more than one sentence
so what do we do we append sentences and
we express the order by numbering them
so that's how you find your
way through the domain story
now the pictographic language is just
one aspect of the main storytelling
equally if not more important is that it is also a
workshop format a way of bringing people together
and what happens in the minds of the participants
of the bookshop is very important so it's the
picture is not just it's not the only result
also being there being present in the workshop
if you miss this campfire experience
it's not the same just looking at
the result showing the picture to
someone who was not at a workshop
that's not the same as actually
being there and contributing to it
so what do we need for a workshop well we
need people to tell us a story the story tells
and what is a storyteller
without someone who listens so
we need listeners our storytellers are usually
the domain experts users stakeholders and
our listeners are usually members of a development
team business analysts usability experts and so on
and often we don't have just one storyteller
but we have several storytellers so every
role that is involved in a business
process can contribute to the story
now storytelling is not just a one-way activity
it's more of a dialogue of a discussion
so storytellers or domain experts are not always
born storytellers so they needs a little help
that's where moderator comes comes in handy
and also the listeners can ask questions to
move disturbing forward so typically we would
ask what's happening next or how do you know
that you have to do this now or where do you get
the information from to write it down somewhere
and so on so we want the vivid conversation
that moves forward and while the story is
told it is important that it is also visualized
and that's again a job that the moderator has
so we visualize the story using the pictographic
language while it is told so that gives everyone a
chance to see if we understood the story correctly
or after any mistakes in it so what will happen is
that the domain experts so tell us say oh no you
missed a step or no that's not what i said i used
a different word or can you draw the arrow to can
you turn it around this is wrong so this is very
available and immediate feedback that we get for
that to work everyone needs to be able to see the
visualized story so we use tools for that for
example we can use whiteboards and sticky notes
or digital blackboards or we could use the tool
that uh i used to show you the old work story
it's called egon i o it's open source runs in your
browser you can check it out econo is also the url
now there's a lot more of course to
discuss and learn about domain storytelling
i've written a book about this method together
with my colleague henning schwentner so if you are
curious go and check out domainstorytelling.org
you will find all sorts of links there including
links to the book and you can even save some
money if you buy directly from edison wesley via
the informant store you can use this component
called domain story and get a nice discount
now how has domain storytelling influenced ddd
and how is d2d influenced domain storytelling
well so far i haven't really talked about ddd
in fact i've barely even talked about software
or developing software or modeling software
and that is because domain storytelling
is a modeling method that helps you to have
meaningful conversations about business processes
so building software for this processes is just
one of many use cases for the main storytelling
you could use it to analyze weaknesses and
problems or you could use it to help newly
hired employees to learn about your business
people do that and you're happy with it
however i mostly use it in
software development projects
and there are some projects where
i use domain storytelling like this
so i would start with analyzing the domain
analyzing the problem spaced as is situation
modeling it together with the domain experts so
we get a couple of domain stories out from that
that is something that we can learn from get
feedback from we used it as a basis to design
a new improved process software supported process
we model that with to be domain stories that show
us the future situation again we get feedback
from that we use that to derive requirements
on a course grade or a medium grade level for
example user stories or use cases and again we get
feedback on those requirements and then we build
software and of course we develop it iteratively
and incrementally that means we only take a
couple of those requirements and refine them
and when you go to the next sprint iteration we
take another set of requirements and refine them
so it's a constant process of refinement
now this process is or this description
of software development is not entirely
wrong but it's certainly not completely
right it's it's a bit too waterfally for me
and that changed with the main driven design
in more and more of my projects i get to use ddd
and eric evans provided his own metaphor
for the software development cycle
and that metaphor is the model exploration
whirlpool and it looks like that
so the whirlpool metaphor suggests
that there are interconnected cycles
of storytelling modeling and coding and it
is about learning and about making mistakes
so we have activities that focus on housing
and documenting scenarios and modeling them
telling stories walking through them refocus
proposing models explore the language and take
those models turn them into code learn from that
experiment then go back to your scenarios and
model more scenarios and other cases and so on so
it's this constant whirlpool i think this model
captures much better what is actually going on
in a ddd style development project on the other
hand this model is not as neat as the one i showed
you before it looks a bit messy and maybe that is
the reason why this metaphor is often neglected
when people talk about ddd yet i think the more
the more i think about it the more i reflect on it
the more powerful this metaphor becomes for me and
i mean it's easy to see that when you highlight
how often the term scenario or story appears
in the in the whirlpool that there's a connection
to the main storytelling so for me domain
storytelling fills this gap of how to actually
gather my my scenarios how do i model them
but how to return them how bring how do i
bring them closer to developing software
so that's a way that domain storytelling can help
with this model exploration whirlpool makes it
more tangible but it also had an influence
on domain storytelling because it helps me
to better understand how to integrate the main
storytelling into the domain driven design process
and it helps me to choose the right scope
for a story so which level of granularity
am i interested in am i analyzing the current
process or am i deciding a new process and so
on so i think this is very helpful for that
for choosing the right scope of a story
now the second aspect that has influenced the main
storytelling and the development of
the method is collaborative modeling
before i became a ddd practitioner and a ddd coach
i was active in the academic modeling community
and the software and enterprise architecture
communities and in the requirements engineering
community and i always felt a bit like an outsider
in and one of the reasons why this is different
with the ddd community is that ddd practitioners
have realized the value of collaborative modeling
while i had felt that for some time it really
became evident to me at explore ddd conference
in the u.s where paul raynor drew this picture
it shows collaborative modeling is one of the
most important concepts of ddd it's one of
its pillars so i felt right at home of course
while i'd felt that for some
time that collaborative modeling is an
important pillar of ddd i think that many people
use it synonymously with a brainstorming
ever since alberto pandolini came up with it
so i use events dormant too
here you see my colleagues
in a big picture event storming
session or some of my colleagues
and i think of it as well
i have a modeling toolbox
and in this toolbox there are several tools like
event storming and domain storytelling and um
i think that in many projects you will have to use
more than one modeling method and you definitely
have an advantage if there are several tools in
your toolbox and you know how to choose between
those tools and when to choose which tool that
will increase your changes your chance of success
now thinking of it as a toolbox is one way of
seeing it but i think collaborative modeling
could also be described as a family of methods
with different relationships between them and
the more i became experienced with ddd the more
i looked at collaborative modeling as this family
so in my mind i would say that by now i see
software development as a series of conversations
that are aided by modeling with different
members of this collaborative modeling
family so with different tools
the community behind those methods or tools
they've started to write a book called
the visual collaborate collaboration
tools book you can find it on leanpub
and download it from there so this is a really
thriving community and it's great to see
um that this family is ever expanding and to
see new connections made between those tools
so this is definitely something
that has influenced me a lot
now the final thought i want
to share with you today is
one of the most important concepts i think in ddd
and that is that language and models are bounded
by the context so this is really an eye opener
i mean words can mean different
things to different people
right so even if those people work in the same
organization they might have different ideas
for example in our movie theater what could ticket
mean so for one person it could be a sellable unit
that generates a profit and for the other person
it could mean a piece of paper that is validated
in order to grant access to a movie theater so if
you look at this course-grade domain story from
before again cashier might think of the ticket as
something that they sell it has a price and so on
and they are sure well they are not really
interested in the price they are just
checking if it's the right date and time right
movie and then the ground access so they both
say ticket but they mean different concepts when
they mean ticket now this will often happen in
coarse grained domain stories or also other
collaborative modelling techniques that when
you have different stakeholders to use the same
terms without meaning exactly the same thing
and this is not necessarily a problem especially
on this core screen level but i'll i want to show
you an example where it really was a problem
for me to moderate the modeling session because
there was an immediate problem that luckily i
could resolve with the help of bounded contexts
so this is yet another domain that
tell you about this time it's a
fixtures company called awesome browser games
so a company that provides a platform for
playing browser games but it's based on a true
story so in the workshop in a real workshop we
got different people from different departments
together domain expert software developers
and we wanted to start with a course grain
domain story that shows us an end-to-end
process so a first-term user signs up plays
their first game gets built for the game
so someone started and say well the first step
is that the user opens an account with awesome
browser games and immediately someone said no they
said no the account is much is created much later
i know that for a fact but the first person
replied no no no no you are wrong this is the
first step i know it i know that for a fact this
is the first thing that we do we open the account
well in the words of martin fowler
single conceptual model is a tricky piece to
work with and that was what we were trying to
do here build a single conceptual model
for terms that could not be reconciled
so bounded contexts to the rescue what
did we do to resolve this situation
move on forward well i said okay let's assume
for a moment that the first person is right
and that the account is open in the first step
and then the continued modeling and eventually
arrived at uh the step here the step five in the
picture where the second person thinks that their
account is created and we used different icons
to show that we mean different things here so
different kinds of accounts possibly and
when we talked about it it became evident
that one person thought about the account in
the context of use user registration and the
other person was thinking about accounts in
the context of what we call the game management
so there are actually two kinds of accounts here
one that are per user and the other one is per
user and per game so if you play different games
you have different accounts one for each game
so luckily we had this concept of bounded
context that helped us to resolve this issue
otherwise i don't think the workshop would
have been a success but with this revelation
and we could move on forward
and had a successful workshop
and actually you can use this kind of differences
in languages to spot and find and identify
bounded context so that's also a way how we use
domain storytelling for finding bounded contexts
you've you've actually seen
another example already
where we used bounded context and we remodeled
them in a domain story and that was of course the
cinema example so again on the left in the
course grain story we see in the rectangles
different contexts so we have ticket
sales and snack sales and entrance control
and in the more detailed domain story that story
plays within one context within the ticket sales
context and of course we want to make sure that
within the ticket sales context we have the same
idea of the of the terms that are used there
so that we need our ubiquitous language right
so these are the three things where i think
ddd has really influenced domain storytelling
and influenced its development and also my
personal modeling practices so we have this idea
of the model exploration whirlpool a powerful
metaphor a bit neglected in the ddd community
sadly and we have this this big big community of
collaborative modeling that is not only within ddd
but also extending to other communities like
behavior different development for example
and we have this game-changing concept of
bounded context so the idea that language
and models are bounded by the context
that really changed my modeling practices
now if you want to know more about domain
storytelling go check out domainstorytelling.org
you will find my slides on speaker deck and now
i'm looking forward for your questions thank you
okay thank you very much about dr steven overstory
and right now let me see what's
question that the participants asked
so there are a lot of questions on slido
right yeah okay can you see my screen
yes i can okay the first question is i saw there
is no round trip between each component could you
tell us what motivated you to create create this
one-way direction to express the message flow
so i think this question refers to the roadwork
construction example that i gave if i'm correct
um yeah so um this is something very
typical uh for software developers
we often think in this kind of request response a
pattern um or yeah or like you you call a method
and then you get a return value or something like
that i mean um you can use the main storytelling
in that way but often i think it's the better
idea to to use it to express an intention
otherwise the the picture becomes very messy
with a lot of back and forth and back and forth
and back and forth without really gaining without
pushing the story forward so the idea is that you
express intention and not necessarily things like
um you know you enter something in the system in
the web page you press the button and then the
web page renders a new html page and then you
press the next button and then it renders a new
html page this would be very boring that's not a
good story there's not a lot of information in it
that's that drives the conversation forward um so
that's what i want to avoid and i focus more on
what is the intention of this step and then it's
okay to have just a one-way information flow or
one way direction yeah so that's that's the idea
okay thank you for your answer and
the second question is have you ever
have you ever met someone asking about
the compression between domestic 12
domestory telling and even
swarming how do you think about it
again that is a very common question and
as you saw in the in the slides uh i put
one picture of our event stopping session
in there that i facilitated so i use both
methods plus many more i would say for the last
three years or so i've used event storming and
domain storytelling about uh to the same
amount like 50 50 something like that
there is an overlap there are situations where you
can use one or the other and will still get a good
result out of it but there are also situations
where i think one is better than the other and one
of the indicators for me is what is this process
about or what information are you looking um
to to learn what what are interested in if it's
about many people collaborating with each other
so if you have a business process it involves
many people or even many software systems and
information goes from one person to the next and
back and you're interested in the communication
patterns and and learning how people collaborate
then i think domain storytelling is the better
approach because the story is centered
around the the people around the actors
and you can really see who is doing what with
whom if on the other hand you're more interested
in this time series like in in rainstorming you
have this timeline from left to right and status
changes and this happened better and that happened
that happened that event storming is is i think
the better approach but as i said um i use i use
both there are situations where you can use both
and you can also combine it for example in the
project that i'm currently working on we started
with domain storytelling to figure out the the
process that this new software system should build
and then the development team decided they want to
implement the software using event sourcing so for
big picture level we had domain stories and for
design level uh for the system design we switched
to event streaming because it fits much better to
an event-sourced way of building systems there are
more ways to combine it i have to refer you to the
book for that we have a couple of examples there
um yeah so okay thank you very much okay um the
first question is can domestory trolling can use
as a metastatology or a tool for class design
in the implementation of ddd technical design
i think there was a follow-up from
kim in the in the chat so it depends on different
perspective and how much focus you're looking
for in time series consequences or
the actors relationships yes yes
i think that's right that's uh it's a
good summary okay now to the next question
sorry so can the mentor telling be used as a
methodology or tool for class design yes it can
the funny thing about it is that domain
storytelling well its predecessors are
actually rather old so the first ancestor the
first predecessor is from the 1990s and it was
heavily influenced by object oriented modeling so
you can still still see that influence and i think
it is suitable as a tool for class modeling when
you want an object oriented approach and it also
fits nicely into the the ddd thinking because
you can look at the work objects and say okay
this is going to be either an entity or aggregate
or maybe a value object and the arrows that depict
the activities well those are the um that is the
behavior of the entities and the work objects
so um for example in this construction example we
had permits and we had hearings and the hearing
was started then statements um are considered
and these are all the things that later become
entities and aggregates so a hearing for example
we model the hearing it's an aggregate and and
stuff like that so that works um what do you need
for that you need to main storytelling that you
so you need the main stories that are rather
fine-grained so if you're on a very overview
level this wouldn't work but if if you model it
rather fine-drained then you have enough language
and enough expressiveness in the model that
you can defer object-oriented design from that
okay thank you very much and the next question
is domestic trolling as a methodology of
implementing ddd what do you think is
advantage and what about the disadvantage
most of the time i used to mean storytelling
as a communication tool and the thing that
is apart from what i just explained from that
from the previous question with how you can use
it to implement it but mostly um i think it's
about bringing people people together having
meaningful conversations about the domain and
that is something that domain storytelling is uh
really good at helping with this so this would be
the the main advantage and um then you can drive
the conversation into different directions for
example you can use it to find uh bounded contexts
so that would be a typical way of using it uh to
implement ddd or you can use it on a lower level
um to to come up with object oriented design
using entities and aggregates and so on
what about disadvantages well i'm a
bit biased here of course i really
love the main storytelling so it's it's
hard to think about disadvantages but
now with the feedback okay um but
um well maybe let's put it this way
it's not the right tool for everything so
that's why i always talk about this toolbox
and um i've had situations where i thought using
this this modeling method is a good idea and
then we go into the workshop and it just doesn't
work for some reason for for whatever reason and
then it's always good if you have this toolbox
of other modeling tools and say okay i'm sorry
this conversation is not going forward but i
have an idea uh let's use for example let's
use example mapping to to to figure that out or
let's use event storming and then you can switch
so um i think this would be a disadvantage like
um treating it as a one-size-fits-all tool for
every situation that's not going to work you
you will need different tools in your toolbox
okay and then the next is uh
domestic trolling suitable as a ddd
implementation necessary complex domain
such as the banking or financial industry
yes i think so for complex domains
my colleagues and i have have used
this technique and its predecessors
for uh 15 years and we applied it in complex
domains like healthcare banking insurance
managing ports for example we had stuff like
disaster management disaster disaster response
teams so a whole lot of different domains
logistics of course um e-commerce so it's not
really bound to one domain it's really for for
pretty much every domain so i have not encountered
a domain yet where i say okay this doesn't
fit here um yeah so i would definitely to
say this is uh usable in complex domains
okay thank you for your presentation um have you
run into a suitable where one object can either be
a working object or an actor in different sequence
of one dst image how do we deal with it it's a
good question it's already a bit advanced so well
within the domain of course it can happen that um
in in one domain story something is an
actor and in one domain is something is
a work object similarly to in in one valid
context you can model something as an entity
and in the next bounded context it's a
value object because it doesn't change
so that's possible but this question is
about in the same picture in the same domain
again this is not a common case but it can
happen for example um if we think about
something like user management user registration
you sign up for something you are the user you're
the actor then i'm only as an actor and you open
your account and then the system um creates a user
as a representation of the of the human being
then we have user as an actor and then we have
user as a work object with the same picture but
that's not a problem at all you just have to use
a different icon to represent that so i would use
this little stick figure for the for the actor
for the person and um for example the icon set
that i use that's the google material i can set
they have another smaller picture of a user with
a little check mark and that's the one that i
typically use for stuff like um user account um so
that's um that's the way um how i deal with it so
use different icons to represent those
different concepts and then it works
okay
as the realization of protons or service
product methodology or tool does domain
storytelling usually it's a great with to
foreign or complete agile development process
from requirements analysis to system development
uh very nice so um
one of the tools of the methods that i use um
a lot in combination with domain storytelling
is user story mapping why
because of two reasons so
domain storytelling is always
about scenarios so about typically